<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/dev/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The treatise of Lorenzo Valla on the  donation of Constantine: text and translation into English</title>
        <author>Lorenzo Valla</author>
        <editor n="transl" role="translator">Christopher B. Coleman, Ph.D., Professor of History in Allegheny College </editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The treatise of Lorenzo Valla on the  donation of Constantine: text and translation into English</title>
            <author>Lorenzo Valla</author>
            <respStmt>
              <name>Christopher B. Coleman, Ph.D., Professor of History in Allegheny College</name>
              <resp>translator</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
              <date>1922</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
	<ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/cu31924029363706">Hathi Trust http://hdl.handle.net/2027/cu31924029363706</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="Chapter"
                         matchPattern="(\\w+).(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\']/tei:div[@n=\'$2\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter</p> </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Book"
                         matchPattern="(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <p>This text is quickly corrected OCR output. The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the
                CTS/CITE Architecture.</p>
</encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="ger">German</language>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
        <language ident="ita">Italian</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>

<pb n="9"/>



<pb n="11"/>



<head>The donation of Constantine 

as given in part one, division XCVI, 

chapters XIII and XIV of Gratian's 

Decretum, or Harmony of the 

Canons. 

Part one. Division XCVI. </head>

<p>[PALEA #1 
CHAPTER XIII. CONCERNING THE SAME.2 

The Emperor Constantine yielded his crown, and all his 
royal prerogatives in the city of Rome, and in Italy, and 
in western parts to the Apostolic [See] . For in the Acts 
of the Blessed Sylvester (which the Blessed Pope Gelasius in the 
Council of the Seventy Bishops recounts as read by the catholic, 
and in accordance with ancient usage many churches he says 
follow this example) occurs the following:] </p>

<p>[PALEA. 
C. XIV. CONCERNING THE SAME.</p>

<p>The Emperor Constantine the fourth day after his baptism 
conferred this privilege on the Pontiff of the Roman church, 
that in the whole Roman world priests should regard him as 

<note xml:id="note.11.1"><p> The meaning of this word in this connection is unknown. The chapters to  which it is prefixed are for the most part supposed to have been early marginal  annotations afterwards incorporated in the text of the Decretum. Cf. Friedberg, Corpus Iuris Canonici, vol. I, Prolegomena, p. Ixxxvi. 

</p></note>

<note xml:id="note.11.2"><p> The subject of chapters xi and xii is, "The Emperors must be under the Pontiffs, not over them." Chapters xiii and xiv continue the same subject. 

</p></note>



<pb n="13"/>


their head, as judges do the king. In this privilege among other 
things is this: "We — together with all our satraps, and the whole 
senate and my nobles, and also all the people subject to the 
government of glorious Rome — considered it advisable, that as the 
Blessed Peter is seen to have been constituted vicar of the Son 
of God on the earth, so the Pontiffs who are the representatives 
of that same chief of the apostles, should obtain from us and our 
empire the power of a supremacy greater than the clemency of 
our earthly imperial serenity is seen to have conceded to it, 
choosing that same chief of the apostles and his vicars to be our 
constant intercessors with God. And to the extent of our earthly 
imperial power, we have decreed that his holy Roman church 
shall be honored with veneration, and that more than our empire 
and earthly throne the most sacred seat of the Blessed Peter 
shall be gloriously exalted, we giving to it power, and dignity of 
glory, and vigor, and honor imperial. And we ordain and decree 
that he shall have the supremacy as well over the four principal 
seats, Alexandria, Antioch, Jerusalem, and Constantinople, as 
also over all the churches of God in the whole earth. And the 
Pontiff, who at the time shall be at the head of the holy Roman 
church itself, shall be more exalted than, and chief over, all the 
priests of the whole world, and according to his judgment everyr 
thing which is provided for the service of God and for the 
stability of the faith of Christians is to be administered. And 
below: §. i. On the churches of the blessed apostles Peter and 
Paul, for the providing of the lights, we have conferred landed 
estates of possessions, and have enriched them with different 
objects, and through our sacred imperial mandate we have granted 
him of our property in the east as well as in the west, and even 
in the northern and the southern quarter; namely, in Judea, 
Greece, Asia, Thrace, Africa, and Italy and the various islands; 
under this condition indeed, that all shall be administered by the 
hand of our most blessed father the supreme Pontiff, Sylvester, 
and his successors. And below: §. 2. And to our Father, the 
Blessed Sylvester, supreme Pontiff and Pope universal, of the 
city of Rome, and to all the Pontiffs, his successors, who shall sit 



<pb n="15"/>


in the seat of the Blessed Peter even unto the end of the world, 
we by this present do give our imperial Lateran palace, then the 
diadem, that is, the crown of our head, and at the same time the 
tiara and also the shoulder-band, — that is, the strap that usually 
surrounds our imperial neck; and also the purple mantle and 
scarlet tunic, and all the imperial raiment; and also the same rank 
as those presiding over the imperial cavalry, conferring also even 
the imperial scepters, and at the same time all the standards, and 
banners, and the different ornaments, and all the pomp of our 
imperial eminence, and the glory of our power. §.3. We decree 
moreover, as to the most reverend men, the clergy of different 
orders who serve that same holy Roman church, that they have 
that same eminence, distinction, power and excellence, by the 
glory of which it seems proper for our most illustrious senate to 
be adorned; that is, that they be made patricians and consuls, and 
also we have proclaimed that they be decorated with the other 
imperial dignities. And even as the imperial militia is adorned, so 
also we decree that the clergy of the holy Roman church be 
adorned. And even as the imperial power is adorned with different
offices, of chamberlains, indeed, and door-keepers, and all 
the guards, so we wish the holy Roman church also to be decorated.
And in order that the pontifical glory may shine forth most 
fully, we decree this also; that the horses of the clergy of this 
same holy Roman church be decorated with saddle-cloths and 
linens, that is, of the whitest color, and that they are to so ride. 
And even as our senate uses shoes with felt socks, that is, distinguished
by white linen, so the clergy also should use them, so 
that, even as the celestial orders, so also the terrestrial may be 
adorned to the glory of God. §. 4. Above all things, moreover, we 
give permission to that same most holy one our Father Sylvester 
and to his successors, from our edict, that he may make priest 
whomever he wishes, according to his own pleasure and counsel, 
and enroll him in the number of the religious clergy [i.e., regular, 
or monastic, clergy; or, perhaps, the cardinals], let no one whomsoever
presume to act in a domineering way in this. §. 5. We 
also therefore decreed this, that he himself and his successors 



<pb n="17"/>


might use and bear upon their heads — to the praise of God for 
the honor of the Blessed Peter — the diadem, that is, the crown 
which we have granted him from our own head, of purest gold 
and precious gems. But since he himself, the most blessed Pope, 
did not at all allow that crown of gold to be used over the clerical 
crown which he wears to the glory of the Blessed Peter, we placed 
upon his most holy head, with our own hands, a glittering tiara 
of dazzling white representing the Lord's resurrection, and holding
the bridle of his horse, out of reverence for the Blessed Peter, 
we performed for him the duty of groom, decreeing that all his 
successors, and they alone, use this same tiara in processions in 
imitation of our power. §. 6. Wherefore, in order that the supreme 
pontificate may not deteriorate, but may rather be adorned with 
glory and power even more than is the dignity of an earthly rule; 
behold, we give over and relinquish to the aforesaid our most 
blessed Pontiff, Sylvester, the universal Pope, as well our palace, 
as has been said, as also the city of Rome, and all the provinces, 
places and cities of Italy and the western regions, and we decree 
by this, our godlike and pragmatic sanction that they are to be 
controlled by him and by his successors, and we grant that they 
shall remain under the law of the holy Roman church. §.7. Wherefore
we have perceived it to be fitting that our empire and the 
power of our kingdom should be transferred in the regions of the 
East, and that in the province of Byzantia, in the most fitting 
place, a city should be built in our name, and that our empire 
should there be established, for where the supremacy of priests 
and the head of the Christian religion has been established by 
the heavenly Emperor, it is not right that there an earthly 
emperor should have jurisdiction. §. 8. We decree, moreover, that 
all these things, which through this our sacred imperial [charter] 
and through other godlike decrees we have established and con-' 
firmed, remain inviolate and unshaken unto the end of the world.' 
Wherefore, before the living God who commanded us to reign, 
and in the face of his terrible judgment, we entreat, through this 
our imperial sanction, all the emperors our successors, and all the 
nobles, the satraps also, the most glorious senate, and all the 



<pb n="19"/>


people in the whole world, now and in all times still #1 to come 
subject to our rule, that no one of them in any way be allowed 
either to break these [decrees], or in any way overthrow them. 
If any one, moreover, — which we do not believe — prove a scorner 
or despiser in this matter, he shall be subject and bound over to 
eternal damnation, and shall feel the holy ones of God, the chief  
of the apostles, Peter and Paul, opposed to him in the present and 
in the future life, and he shall be burned in the lower hell and 
shall perish with the devil and all the impious. The page, moreover,
of this our imperial decree, we, confirming it with our own 
hands, did place above the venerable body of the Blessed Peter, 
chief of the apostles. Given at Rome on the third day before the 
Kalends of April, our master the august Flavius Constantine, for 
the fourth time, and Gallicanus, most illustrious men, being 
consuls."] 

<note xml:id="note.19.1"><p> retro was used at Rome in the latter part of the eighth century with the  peculiar meaning of "still" or "again." This is one of the clues to the date and  place of the document. Henderson's translation is erroneous. 
</p></note>



</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
