<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/dev/tei-epidoc.rng" type="xml"?>
 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The treatise of Lorenzo Valla on the  donation of Constantine: text and translation into English</title>
        <author>Lorenzo Valla</author>
        <editor n="transl" role="translator">Christopher B. Coleman, Ph.D., Professor of History in Allegheny College </editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The treatise of Lorenzo Valla on the  donation of Constantine: text and translation into English</title>
            <author>Lorenzo Valla</author>
            <respStmt>
              <name>Christopher B. Coleman, Ph.D., Professor of History in Allegheny College</name>
              <resp>translator</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
              <date>1922</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
	<ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/cu31924029363706">Hathi Trust http://hdl.handle.net/2027/cu31924029363706</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="Chapter"
                         matchPattern="(\\w+).(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\']/tei:div[@n=\'$2\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter</p> </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Book"
                         matchPattern="(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <p>This text is quickly corrected OCR output. The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the
                CTS/CITE Architecture.</p>
</encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="ger">German</language>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
        <language ident="ita">Italian</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>







<pb n="1"/>






<head>Introductory</head> 

<p>The Donation of Constantine — the most famous forgery 
in European history; papal authority — since the triumph 
of Christianity the most perennial question of European 
society; historical criticism — one of the most comprehensive, most 
alluring, and most baffling enterprises of the modern mind; 
Lorenzo Valla — the greatest of the professional Italian humanists;
these lines of study have converged, accidentally perhaps, to 
call forth the following pages. Much of the subject matter which 
might properly form their introduction I have already treated 
more fully in an earlier work,1 and a brief statement will suffice 
here.</p>

<p>The Donation of Constantine (Constitutum Constantini), 
written probably not long after the middle of the eighth century, 
became widely known through its incorporation in the Pseudo-Isidorian
Decretals (about 847-853). Parts of it were included in 
most of the medieval collections of canon law; Anselm's, Deusdedit's,
and Gratian's great work (the Decretum, or Concordia 
discordantium canonum). It purports to reproduce a legal document
in which the Emperor Constantine the Great, reciting his 
baptism and the cure of his leprosy at the hands of Sylvester, 
Bishop of Rome 314-336, confirmed the privilege of that pontiff 
as head of all the clergy and supreme over the other four patriarchates;
conferred upon him extensive imperial property in various 
parts of the world, especially the imperial Lateran palace, and the 
imperial diadem and tiara, and other imperial insignia; granted 
the Roman clergy the rank of the highest Roman orders and their 

<note xml:id="note.1.1"><p> C. B. Coleman, Constantine the Great and Christianity, three phases: the historical, the legendary, and the spurious. Columbia University Studies in History,  Economics and Public Law, vol. LX, no. i. Columbia University Press, and Longmans, Green and Co., New York, 1914. 



</p></note>

<pb n="2"/>


privileges; gave Sylvester and his successors freedom in consecrating
men for certain orders of the clergy; it tells how he, Constantine,
recognized the superior dignity of the Pope by holding 
the bridle of his horse; grants Sylvester Rome, all of Italy, and 
the western provinces, to remain forever under the control of the 
Roman See; and states his own determination to retire to Byzantium
in order that the presence of an earthly emperor may not 
embarrass ecclesiastical authority. This remarkable document was 
almost universally accepted as genuine from the ninth to the 
fifteenth century.</p>

<p>The question of the position of the bishop of Rome in the Christian
Church lacks but a few generations of being as old as 
Christianity itself. His relation to secular governments became an 
acute problem as soon as the imperial government broke down in 
Italy, and has remained so to the present moment. For centuries 
the Papacy was the strongest institution in western Europe. While 
its control at any one time rested principally on the power it actually
possessed and on the ability of its representatives, legal 
theories and historical documents played a not inconsiderable part 
in its rise and decline. Of these documents the Donation of Constantine
was perhaps the most spectacular, even though it was not 
the most important. It was cited by no less than ten Popes of 
whom we know, to mention no lesser writers, in contentions for 
the recognition of papal control, and contributed not a little to 
the prestige of the Papacy. On the other hand, when its spuriousness
became known, the reaction against it, as in Luther's case, 
contributed powerfully to the revolt from Rome. Its century-long 
influence entitles it to a respect difficult for any one who now reads 
it to feel. And Valla's discussion of it contains many interesting 
reflections on the secular power of the Papacy, perhaps the most 
interesting expression in this connection of fifteenth century 
Italian humanism.</p>

<p>Among the achievements of modern historical criticism Valla's 
work was a conspicuous pioneer. Its quality and its importance 
have often been exaggerated, and as often underestimated. It is 
some satisfaction to make it more generally available in the 



<pb n="3"/>


original text and translation, so that the reader may judge for himself.
A critical appraisal would have to take into account that 
Nicholas Cusanus some seven years earlier in his <title xml:lang="la">De concordantia 
catholica</title> covered part of the same ground even better than Valla 
did, and anticipated some of his arguments. But Valla's treatise is, 
more exhaustive, is in more finished and effective literary form, 
and in effect established for the world generally the proof of the 
falsity of the Donation. Moreover, for the first time, he used effectively
the method of studying the usage of words in the variations 
of their meaning and application, and other devices of internal 
criticism which are the tools of historical criticism to-day. So, 
while Valla's little book may seem slight beside later masterpieces 
of investigation and beside systematic treatises in larger fields, it 
is none the less a landmark in the rise of a new science. I speak 
from personal experience in adding that it is still useful in college 
classes in promoting respect for, and development in, critical 
scholarship.</p>

<p>As to Valla himself the words of Erasmus will bear repetition; 
"Valla, a man who with so much energy, zeal and labor, refuted 
the stupidities of the barbarians, saved half-buried letters from 
extinction, restored Italy to her ancient splendor of eloquence, and 
forced even the learned to express themselves henceforth with 
more circumspection."1 The Italian Renaissance is much extolled 
among us, — and so little known. A short time ago diligent search 
revealed no copy of Valla's works in the United States, and many 
of the larger libraries had none of his separate writings. The same 
is doubtless true in the case of other great names in the Renaissance.
Meanwhile, there are those whose profession it is to teach 
European history and who are utterly unacquainted with medieval 
and later Latin.</p>

<p>The best life of Valla is that by Girolamo Mancini.2 There is no 
satisfactory account of him in English.</p>

<p>Valla wrote his Discourse on the Forgery of the alleged 

<note xml:id="note.3.1"><p> F. M. Nichols, ed., Epistles of Erasmus. Longmans, Green and Co., New York,  1901. 

</p></note>

<note xml:id="note.3.2"><p> Vita di Lorenzo Valla (Florence, 1891).




</p></note>

<pb n="4"/>


Donation of Constantine (<title xml:lang="lat">Declamatio de falso credita et ementita donatione
Constantini</title>, also referred to as <title xml:lang="lat">Libellus</title>, and <title xml:lang="lat">Oratio</title>) in 
1440, when he was secretary to Alfonso, king of Aragon, Sicily, 
and Naples. It may well be considered as part of the campaign 
which that king was conducting against Pope Eugenius IV in 
furtherance of his claims to Italian territories.</p>

<p>There has hitherto been no satisfactory text of this treatise. The 
first printed edition, that of Ulrich von Hutten, in 1517, is excessively
rare, and it, as well as its numerous reprints, is defective 
in places. The same is true of the text in the collected works of 
Valla, the Opera, printed at Basle, 1540, 1543 (?). The only 
English edition, by Thomas Godfray (London, 1525 ?), is rare 
and of no great merit. A modern French edition by <bibl>Alcide Bonneau
(La Donation de Constantin, Paris, 1879)</bibl> gives the text 
with a French translation and a long introduction. It is based on 
the 1520 reprint of Hutten's edition, is polemical, uncritical, and 
admittedly imperfect. A modern edition with translation into 
Italian (<bibl>La dissertazione di Lorenzo Valla su la falsa e manzognera
donazione di Costantino tradotta in Italiano da G. Vincenti, 
Naples, 1895</bibl>) is out of print.</p>

<p>My text is based on the manuscript <bibl>Codex Vaticanus 5314</bibl>, 
dated December 7, 1451, the only complete manuscript of the 
treatise I have been able to find. I have collated this with 
Hutten's text as found in one of the earliest, if not the earliest, 
reprint (contained in the little volume <bibl>De Donatione Constantini 
quid veri habeat, etc., dated 1520</bibl> in the Union Theological Seminary
library copy, but corresponding closely to the one dated 1518 
in E. Bocking's edition of the works of Ulrich von Hutten, vol. I, 
p. 18), and have occasionally used readings from Hutten's text or 
later ones, such as that of Simon Schard,1 but in every instance 
I have indicated the MS. reading. I have used uniform, current 
spelling and punctuation, and have used my own judgment in 
paragraphing.</p>

<p>Preceding Valla's treatise I reprint, with a translation, the text 

<note xml:id="note.4.1"><p> <bibl>Syntagma tractatuum de imperiali iurisdictione, etc., Strassburg, 1609</bibl>; <bibl>first  published under a similar title at Basle, 1566</bibl>. 



</p></note>

<pb n="5"/>


of the Donation as given, with the omission of long sections, in 
Gratian's Decretum, or <title xml:lang="lat">Concordia discordantium canonum</title>, which 
was the form Valla used and on which he based his criticism. I 
take it from <title>A. Friedberg's edition of the Corpus Iuris Canonici, 
vol. I, columns 342-345</title>. The full text of the Donation is best 
given by <bibl>Karl Zeumer, in the Festgabe für Rudolf von Gneist 
(Julius Springer, Berlin, 1888), pp. 47-59</bibl>, reprinted among other 
places in my <bibl><title>Constantine the Great and Christianity</title>, pp. 228-237</bibl>. 
The document may be studied to advantage also in the Decretales 
Pseudo-Isidorianae et Capitula Angilramni, ed. Hinschius (Leipsic,
1863). An English translation, from Zeumer's text, is in <bibl>E. F. 
Henderson's <title>Select Historical Documents of the Middle Ages</title>, 
pp. 319-329</bibl>.</p>

<p>In the translation of passages of the Donation I have, so far as 
possible, used the words of Henderson's translation. In quotations 
from the Bible I have used the King James version. In translating 
Valla's quotations from the Donation I have usually, though not 
always, followed him in giving words their classical and not their 
medieval meaning.</p>

<p>The Donation of Constantine grew out of the legends about 
Sylvester I, Bishop of Rome, as well as out of legends about Constantine.
These are described at length in Constantine the Great 
and Christianity. The most familiar form of the Sylvester-Constantine
legend is that of <bibl>Mombritius' Sanctuarium, sive Vitae 
collectae ex codibus, Milan, c. 1470, vol. II, folio 279: Paris, 1910, 
vol. II, pp. 508-531.</bibl></p>

<p>Present-day scholarship is not in entire agreement on all points 
connected with the Donation of Constantine. The following summary,
however, may be hazarded. The problem of modern criticism,
of course, is, not to establish the spuriousness of the 
Donation, — that has long been obvious, — but to locate the origin 
of the document as closely as possible.</p>

<p>The development of the Sylvester-Constantine legend was 
worked out best by <bibl>Dollinger (Papstfabeln des Mittelalters, Munich,
1863: ed., J. Friedrich, Stuttgart, 1890)</bibl> and by <bibl>Duchesne 
(in his edition of the Liber Pontificalis, vol. I, 1886, pp. cvii-cxx)</bibl>. 



<pb n="6"/>


These have shown the existence at Rome, as early as the last of 
the sixth century, of the story which forms most of the narrative 
part of the Donation, and gave the forger the whole of his background.</p>

<p>The earliest known manuscript of the document is in the Codex 
Parisiensis Lat. 2778, in the Collectio Sancti Dionysii, found in 
the monastery of St. Denis, in France. The collection contains 
documents dating from the last years of the eighth century, though 
it may have been put together later. The collected Pseudo-Isidorean
Decretals, in which the Donation was virtually published 
to the world, in the middle of the ninth century, also came out in 
France. French writers of the ninth century, also, were the first, 
so far as we know, to refer to the Donation. Such facts help to fix 
the date of the forgery, but under the circumstances they do not 
fix the place as France. Rather they are merely another illustration
of the well-known leadership of France in learning and 
politics during the ninth century.</p>

<p>Linguistic peculiarities of the document have been most exhaustively
treated by one of the greatest of critical historians, Paul 
Scheffer-Boichorst,1 not to speak of briefer studies by Dollinger, 
Brunner, and others. In the full text of the Donation, as for instance
the one published by Zeumer, are found many features 
distinctive of Italian documents of the eighth century, and a number
that apparently are peculiar to the chancellery of Stephen II 
(III), Bishop of Rome 752-757, and of Paul I (757-767), more 
particularly the latter. (Some of these do not occur in the passages 
and the text which Valla used; that is, in his copy of Gratian's 
Decretum.) This is true in varying degrees of particularity of the 
form or usage of the following words; synclitus (for senatus) in 
§ 15, banda (for vexillum) in § 14, censura (diploma) in § 17, 
constitutum (decretum) in §§ 17 and 18, retro (applied to the 
future) in §§ 1 and 19, largitas (possessio) in § 13, consul and 

<note xml:id="note.6.1"><p> <bibl>Neue Forschungen uber die Konstantinische Schenkung, in Mittheilungen d.  Instituts für Österr. Geschichtsforschung, vol. X (1889), pp. 325-et seq.,</bibl> <bibl>XI (1890),  pp. 128 et seq</bibl>. <bibl>Reprinted in his Gesammelte Schriften in the Historische Studien of E. Eberling, vol. XLII.</bibl>



</p></note>

<pb n="7"/>


patricius (as mere designations of rank) in § 15, vel (et) in §§ 11, 
12, 13, 16, 19, seu (et) in §§ 14 and 17, satraps (as a Roman 
official) in §§ 8, II, and 19, and inluminator in § 7 in some manuscripts.
The following phrases, also, are more or less distinctive; 
Deo amabilis in § i, Deo vivo qui nos regnare precipit in § 19, uno 
ex eadem sancta Trinitate in § i, principem apostolorum vel eius 
vicarios firmos apud Deum adesse patronos in § 11, pro concinnatione
luminarionim in § 13, et subscriptio imperialis in § 20, propriis
manibus roborantes in § 20, religiosus clericus in § 15. The 
first part of § 4, Tres itaque formae . . . hominem, is very similar 
to part of a letter of Paul I's in 757. In short, the language of the 
Donation seems to point to the papal chancellery as the place of its 
origin, and the pontificate of Paul I (757-767) as the most 
probable time.</p>

<p>That also seems to offer the situation and environment which 
would most naturally call forth the document as we have it. This 
is well brought out by <bibl>Ludo Moritz Hartmann in his Geschichte 
Italiens im Mittelalter,</bibl>1 and by <bibl>Erich Caspar in his Pippin und 
die romische Kirche.</bibl>2 The Papacy was then cutting loose from 
the Emperor at Constantinople and ignoring his representatives in 
Italy, as well as developing its own independent policy toward 
Italian territory, toward the Lombards, and toward the Franks. 
The aim of the forger seems to have been the characteristically 
medieval one of supplying documentary warrant for the existence 
of the situation which had developed through a long-drawn-out 
revolution, namely, the passage of imperial prerogatives and political
control in Italy from the Emperor to the Papacy. Hence, 
along with general statements of papal primacy, and of gifts of 
property, detailed and explicit stress is laid upon the granting of 
imperial honors, the imperial palace, and imperial power to the 
Pope, and upon the right of the Roman clergy to the privileges of 
the highest ranks of Roman society. Legal confirmation was thus 
given for riding roughshod over the vestiges and memories of the 
imperial regime in Italy and for looking to the Papacy as the 

<note xml:id="note.7.1"><p> II, ii (Leipsic, 1903), pp. 218-231. 
</p></note>

<note xml:id="note.7.2"><p> Berlin, 1914, pp. 185-189. 



</p></note>

<pb n="8"/>


source of all honors and dignities. Furthermore we know that 
Paul I was extremely devoted to the memory of Sylvester, and so 
it may well have been under his influence that this document came 
into existence with its tribute to Sylvester's personal character and 
historic significance.</p>

<p>I wish to give public expression of my thanks to Professor 
Deane P. Lockwood, of Columbia University, for his kindness in 
reading my translation of Valla's treatise and the many suggestions
and improvements he indicated; to Professor J. T. Shotwell, 
of Columbia University, who was largely responsible for the beginning
of the whole undertaking; and to Mr. Alexander D. 
Fraser, of Allegheny College, for generous assistance in reading 
proof. 


</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
